<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>HOME on Melvin J Joseph</title>
    <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/</link>
    <description>Recent content in HOME on Melvin J Joseph</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Melvin J Joseph</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://melvin.is-a.dev/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Multi-modal Sports Video Summarization</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/sports-summarization/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Dec 2024 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/sports-summarization/</guid>
      <description>Built a multi-modal pipeline using BERT and CNNs to detect and align important football moments from commentary and scoreboard video. Final output is a stitched highlight video.&#xA;Fine-tuned BERT for audio commentary classification. Used image processing on scoreboard to extract goal/match events. Weighted timestamp fusion for final highlight stitching. UI built using Streamlit for interactive demo. Here&amp;rsquo;s the Architecture of the system:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment-Driven Stock Price Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/stock-forecast/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/stock-forecast/</guid>
      <description>This project involves scraping and curating daily news articles related to Tata Motors and analyzing the sentiment of each article using NLP models from Hugging Face.&#xA;A Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) model was trained to forecast stock price movements based on these sentiments and historical data, revealing the impact of public sentiment on market behavior.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inventory Management System</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/inventory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/inventory/</guid>
      <description>This inventory system was built with a microservices architecture using Flask and RabbitMQ for decoupled inter-service communication. Key services include health checks, item management, stock updates, and order handling.&#xA;MongoDB was used for data persistence with full CRUD support. The entire system is containerized using Docker for seamless deployment across environments.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vinhal</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/vinhal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/vinhal/</guid>
      <description>Vinhal is a basic machine learning library built in Rust and exposed to Python using PyO3 and Maturin. It helps understand ML internals and achieves 50%-90% faster training times than native Python implementations.&#xA;Built without external dependencies. Exposes safe Python bindings via Rust. Trains models super fast. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stock Trading Web-App</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/stock-trading-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/stock-trading-app/</guid>
      <description>The app allows users to view real-time stock prices, buy/sell stocks, and track portfolio allocation using the IEX Cloud API.&#xA;Full PERN stack application. Includes user auth, charts (Chart.js), and allocation tracking. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restaurant Booking App</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/restaurant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/restaurant/</guid>
      <description>Users can reserve tables and manage bookings. Data is stored in MongoDB Atlas, and the UI is deployed via Vercel.&#xA;Mobile-friendly design. Instant table booking. Modern frontend and backend stack. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graduate Admission Predictor</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/graduate-admission/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2022 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/graduate-admission/</guid>
      <description>This Streamlit app predicts the chances of a student getting admitted based on academic metrics like GRE, TOEFL, CGPA, and more.&#xA;Uses linear regression from Scikit-learn. Clean UI and hosted app. </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tic Tac Toe (Socket Programming)</title>
      <link>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/tic-tac-toc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 10:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://melvin.is-a.dev/portfolio/tic-tac-toc/</guid>
      <description>A network-based two-player Tic Tac Toe game using client-server architecture.&#xA;Uses Python socket library. Easy to play over a local network. </description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
